It's 1878.
إنّه عام 1878.
Sir Francis Galton gives a remarkable talk.
ألقى السيد فرانسيس جالتون حديثاً استثنائياً.
He's speaking to the anthropologic institute of Great Britain and Ireland.
في معهد العلوم الإنسانية لأيرلندا وبريطانيا العُظمى
Known for his pioneering work in human intelligence,
والذي عُرف بأعماله الرائدة في مجال الذكاء البشري،
Galton is a brilliant polymath.
جالتون رجل ذكي واسع المعرفة.
He's an explorer,
إنّه مستكشف،
an anthropologist,
عالم في علوم الإنسان،
a sociologist,
وعالم اجتماع،
a psychologist
وعالم نفس
and a statistician.
وعالم إحصاء.
He's also a eugenist.
وكذلك اختصاصي في تحسين النسل.
In this talk,
في هذا الحديث،
he presents a new technique by which he can combine photographs
عرض تقنية جديدة عن كيفية دمج الصور
and produce composite portraits.
وإنتاج صور شخصيّة مركبة.
This technique could be used to characterize different types of people.
هذه التقنيّة يمكن استعمالها لوصف أنواع مختلفة من الناس.
Galton thinks that if he combines photographs of violent criminals,
يعتقد جالتون أنّه إذا جمع صوراً لمجرمين عنيفين،
he will discover the face of criminality.
أنّه سيكتشف الوجه الإجرامي.
But to his surprise,
لكنّ ما أدهشه،
the composite portrait that he produces
أنّ الصور المركبة التي أنتجها
is beautiful.
كانت جميلة.
Galton's surprising finding raises deep questions:
أثار اكتشاف جالتون المدهش الكثير من الأسئلة:
What is beauty?
ما هو الجمال؟
Why do certain configurations of line and color and form excite us so?
لماذا تثيرنا أنماط محددة من الخط واللون والشكل؟
For most of human history,
على مرّ معظم تاريخ البشرية،
these questions have been approached using logic and speculation.
تمَّ تناول هذه الأسئلة باستخدام المنطق والتخمين.
But in the last few decades,
ولكن في العقود القليلة الأخيرة،
scientists have addressed the question of beauty
تناول العلماء سؤال الجمال
using ideas from evolutionary psychology and tools of neuroscience.
باستخدام أفكار من علم النفس التطوري وأدوات من علم الأعصاب.
We're beginning to glimpse the why and the how of beauty,
نحن في بداية معرفة سبب وكيفية الجمال،
at least in terms of what it means for the human face and form.
على الأقل في ما يعنيه الجمال في وجه الإنسان وهيئته.
And in the process,
وخلال هذه العملية،
we're stumbling upon some surprises.
فإننا نتعثر في بعض المفاجآت.
When it comes to seeing beauty in each other,
عندما يتعلق الأمر برؤيتنا الجمال في بعضنا البعض،
while this decision is certainly subjective for the individual,
إذ أنّ هذا القرار يعتبر بالتأكيد قرارًا شخصيًا للفرد،
it's sculpted by factors that contribute to the survival of the group.
إنّها متمثلة في العوامل التي تساهم في بقاء المجموعة.
Many experiments have shown
العديد من التجارب أوضحت
that a few basic parameters contribute to what makes a face attractive.
أنّ بعض المعاييرالمتغيرة الأساسية تساهم في ماذا يجعل الوجه جذاباً.
These include averaging, symmetry and the effects of hormones.
وهذا يشمل التوسط والتناسق وتأثير الهرمونات.
Let's take each one of these in turn.
دعونا نتناول كلّ واحدة منهم على حدة.
Galton's finding
وجد جالتون
that composite or average faces are typically more attractive
أن الوجوه المتوسطة أو المركبة عادة ما تكون أكثر جاذبية
than each individual face that contributes to the average
من كل وجه يساهم في هذا المتوسط على حدة
has been replicated many times.
وقد تم تكرارها عدة مرات.
This laboratory finding fits with many people's intuitions.
اكتشاف المختبر هذا يتوافق مع حدس العديد من الناس.
Average faces represent the central tendencies of a group.
متوسط الوجوه تظهر الميول المركزية للمجموعة
People with mixed features represent different populations,
الأشخاص ذو الملامح الممزوجة يمثلون مجموعات سكانية مختلفة،
and presumably harbor greater genetic diversity
ويفترض أنهم يحتضنون تنوعًا جينيًا رائعًا
and adaptability to the environment.
وقدرة على التأقلم مع البيئة.
Many people find mixed-race individuals attractive
يجد العديد من الناس أن الأفراد ذو الأعراق المختلطة جذابون
and inbred families less so.
والأسر الطبيعية أقل جذباً.
The second factor that contributes to beauty is symmetry.
وثاني عامل يدل على الجمال هو التناسق.
People generally find symmetric faces more attractive than asymmetric ones.
عامةً الناس يجدون الوجوه المتناسقة أكثر جاذبية من غيرها.
Developmental abnormalities are often associated with asymmetries.
عادةً تشوهات النمو ترتبط بعدم التناسق.
And in plants, animals and humans,
يظهر عدم التناسق عند النباتات والحيوانات والإنسان
asymmetries often arise from parasitic infections.
غالبا من العدوى الطفيلية.
Symmetry, it turns out,
يتضح أن التناسق،
is also an indicator of health.
مؤشر للصحة.
In the 1930s,
في عام 1930،
a man named Maksymilian Faktorowicz
أقر شخص يدعى ماكسيميلين فاكتروويز
recognized the importance of symmetry for beauty
بأهمية التناسق للجمال
when he designed the beauty micrometer.
عندما صمم ميكرومتر الجمال.
he could measure minor asymmetric flaws
استطاع أن يقيس خلل عدم التناسق البسيط
which he could then make up for with products he sold from his company,
وبهذا يستطيع تعديله بمنتجاته التي كان يبيعها من شركته،
named brilliantly after himself, Max Factor,
والتي سميت على اسمه "ماكس فاكتور"،
which, as you know, is one of the world's most famous brands
كما نعلم أنها الآن من أشهر الماركات في العالم
for "make up."
لمستحضرات التجميل.
The third factor that contributes to facial attractiveness
والعامل الثالث الذي يساهم في جاذبية الوجه
is the effect of hormones.
هو تأثير الهرمونات.
And here, I need to apologize for confining my comments
وهنا اعتذر لأن تعليقاتي ستقتصر
to heterosexual norms.
على معايير غيريي الجنس.
But estrogen and testosterone play important roles
ولكن هرموني الإستروجين والتيستوستيرون يلعبان أدوارًا مهمة
in shaping features that we find attractive.
في تكوين الملامح التي تجعلنا نراها جذابة.
Estrogen produces features that signal fertility.
الإستروجين ينتج ملامح تشير إلى الخصوبة.
Men typically find women attractive
إجمالا الرجال ينجذبون إلى النساء
who have elements of both youth and maturity.
اللاتي تكون لديهن عوامل الطفولة والنضج معا.
A face that's too baby-like might mean that the girl is not yet fertile,
الوجه شبيه الطفولي الذي يجعلك تشعر أن الفتاة ليست خصبة،
so men find women attractive
إذاً الرجال يجدون النساء جذابات
who have large eyes, full lips and narrow chins
من تمتلك عينان واسعتان، شفاه ممتلئة وذقن صغير
as indicators of youth,
كمؤشرات على الشباب.
and high cheekbones as an indicator of maturity.
وعظام فك مرتفعة كمؤشر للنضوج.
Testosterone produces features that we regard as typically masculine.
ينتج هرمون التستوستيرون ملامح نعتبرها ذكورية.
These include heavier brows,
والتي تشمل جبهة أعرض،
thinner cheeks
وخدود أنحف
and bigger, squared-off jaws.
وفكين أكبرعلى شكل مربع.
But here's a fascinating irony.
ولكن هناك سخرية رائعة هنا.
In many species,
في عديد من الأجناس
if anything,
على أي حال،
testosterone suppresses the immune system.
التستوستيرون يقوم بقمع الجهاز المناعي.
So the idea that testosterone-infused features are a fitness indicator
وبالتالي فإن فكرة أن التستوستيرون تعزز مؤشرات اللياقة البدنية
doesn't really make a whole lot of sense.
ليست منطقية بالكامل.
Here, the logic is turned on its head.
هنا، ينقلب المنطق رأساً على عقب.
Instead of a fitness indicator,
بدلاً من مؤشر اللياقة،
scientists invoke a handicap principle.
اعتمد العلماء على أنه مبدأ عائق.
The most commonly cited example of a handicap
وأوضح مثال للعائق هو
is the peacock's tail.
ذيل الطاووس.
This beautiful but cumbersome tail doesn't exactly help the peacock
جميل ولكن الذيل الثقيل لا يساعد الطاووس
avoid predators
لتجنب الحيوانات المفترسة
and approach peahens.
والاقتراب من أُنثى الطاووس.
Why should such an extravagant appendage evolve?
لما يجب أن ينمو شيء مُسرف كهذا؟
Even Charles Darwin,
حتى تشارلز داروين،
in an 1860 letter to Asa Gray wrote
في عام 1860 أرسل خطاباً إلى اسا جراي
that the sight of the peacock's tail made him physically ill.
كتب فيه أن منظر ذيل الطاووس جعله يمرض.
He couldn't explain it with his theory of natural selection,
ولم يستطع شرحه في نظريته عن الإنتقاء الطبيعي.
and out of this frustration,
وبعيداً عن إحباطه،
he developed the theory of sexual selection.
قام بتطوير نظريته عن الإنتقاء الجنسي.
On this account,
في هذا الحسبان،
the display of the peacock's tail is about sexual enticement,
أن ذيل الطاووس كان للجذب الجنسي،
and this enticement means it's more likely the peacock will mate
وهذا الإغواء يعني أن الطاووس سيقوم بالتزاوج
and have offspring.
وإنتاج النسل.
Now, the modern twist on this display argument
والآن النظرية الحديثة الجدلية في ما يخص هذا الأمر
is that the peacock is also advertising its health to the peahen.
أن الطاووس أيضا يُعلن صحته لأنثى الطاووس.
Only especially fit organisms can afford to divert resources
كائنات خاصة فقط تستطيع تحويل الموارد
to maintaining such an extravagant appendage.
للاحتفاظ بمُلحق باذخ كهذا الذيل
Only especially fit men can afford the price that testosterone levies
وفقط الرجال المتناسقين يمكنهم تحمل ضريبة التيستوستيرون
on their immune system.
في نظامهم المناعي.
And by analogy, think of the fact
وبالتناظر، فكروا بالحقيقة القائلة
that only very rich men can afford to pay more than $10,000 for a watch
أن فقط الرجال الأغنياء يمكنهم شراء ساعة بمبلغ أكثر من 10,000دولار
as a display of their financial fitness.
كرمز لتناسقهم المالي.
Now, many people hear these kinds of evolutionary claims
العديد من الناس سمع عن التطور الادعائي الثوري
and think they mean that we somehow are unconsciously seeking mates
وفكروا بمعناها أننا لاشعوريا نبحث عن شركاء
who are healthy.
أصحاء.
And I think this idea is probably not right.
وأظن أن هذه الفكرة غير صحيحة نوعا ما.
Teenagers and young adults are not exactly known for making decisions
المراهقين والشباب غير معروفين بأخذهم قرارات
that are predicated on health concerns.
تستند إلى المخاوف الصحية.
But they don't have to be,
ولكن لا يجب عليهم ذلك،
and let me explain why.
دعوني أشرح لكم لماذا.
Imagine a population
تخيل عدد سكاني
in which people have three different kinds of preferences:
حيث يوجد هناك ثلاث أنواع من الإختيارات:
for green, for orange and for red.
الأخضر والبرتقالي والأحمر.
From their point of view,
ومن وجهة نظرهم،
these preferences have nothing to do with health;
أن هذه الاختيارات ليس لها علاقة بالصحة.
they just like what they like.
هم فقط يُعجبهم ما يُعجبهم.
But if it were also the case that these preferences are associated
ولكن في حال كانت هذه الاختيارات ستكون متصلة
with the different likelihood of producing offspring --
باحتمالات مختلقة من إنتاج النسل.
let's say in a ratio of 3:2:1 --
لنقل أنه في معدل 3:2:1
then in the first generation,
ثم في أول جيل،
there would be 3 greens to 2 oranges to 1 red,
سيكون هناك 3 أخضر إلى 2 برتقالي إلى 1 أحمر،
and in each subsequent generation,
ولكل جيل لاحق،
the proportion of greens increase,
نسبة الأخضر تزداد،
so that in 10 generations,
إذاً خلال عشرة أجيال،
98 percent of this population has a green preference.
98% من السكان يفضلون الأخضر.
Now, a scientist coming in and sampling this population
أخذ عالم عينات من هذه المجموعة
discovers that green preferences are universal.
واكتشف أن الإتجاه الأخضر عالمي.
So the point about this little abstract example
الفكرة وراء هذا المثال التجريدي
is that while preferences for specific physical features
هو أنه في حين أن وجود تفضيلات معينة شكلية
can be arbitrary for the individual,
من الممكن أن تكون طاغية في الفرد،
if those features are heritable
وإذا كانت هذه الملامح وراثية
and they are associated with a reproductive advantage,
ومتصلة بميزات تكاثرية،
over time,
مع مرور الوقت،
they become universal for the group.
تصبح عالمية في المجموعة.
So what happens in the brain when we see beautiful people?
إذاً ما الذي يحدث للدماغ عندما نرى أشخاصًا جميلين؟
Attractive faces activate parts of our visual cortex
الوجوه الجذابة تنشط القشرة البصرية لدينا
in the back of the brain,
في الجزء الخلفي من الدماغ،
an area called the fusiform gyrus,
المنطقة التي تدعى التلفيف المغزلي،
that is especially tuned to processing faces,
وهي منطقة خاصة بمعالجة الوجوه،
and an adjacent area called the lateral occipital complex,
ومنطقة مجاورة تدعى القذالية الجانبية المعقدة
that is especially attuned to processing objects.
وهي منطقة خاصة بمعالجة الأشياء،
In addition,
وبالإضافة لذلك،
attractive faces activate parts of our reward and pleasure centers
تُنشط الوجوه الجذابة أجزاء من مركز السعادة والعطاء لدينا
in the front and deep in the brain,
في المنطقة الأمامية والعميقة من الدماغ،
and these include areas that have complicated names,
وذلك يشمل مناطق لها أسماء معقدة،
like the ventral striatum,
مثل المخطط البطني،
the orbitofrontal cortex
القشرة الجبهية،
and the ventromedial prefrontal cortex.
والقشرة الفصية الجبهية.
Our visual brain that is tuned to processing faces
دماغنا البصري الذي يقوم بمعالجة الوجوه،
interacts with our pleasure centers
يتفاعل مع مراكز السعادة لدينا
to underpin the experience of beauty.
لتحسين المعرفة في الجمال.
Amazingly, while we all engage with beauty,
المذهل، أنه بينما نحن جميعنا ننجذب إلى الجمال،
without our knowledge,
بدون وعي منا،
beauty also engages us.
الجمال كذلك ينجذب لنا.
Our brains respond to attractive faces
تستجيب أدمغتنا للوجوه الجذابة
even when we're not thinking about beauty.
حتى عندما لا نفكر في الجمال.
We conducted an experiment in which people saw a series of faces,
أجرينا تجربة حيث رأى الناس سلسلة من الوجوه،
and in one condition,
وفي حالة واحدة،
they had to decide if a pair of faces were the same or a different person.
كان عليهم أن يُقرروا ما إذا كان زوجان من الوجوه هي لنفس الشخص أو لشخص آخر.
Even in this condition,
وحتى في هذه الحالة،
attractive faces drove neural activity robustly in their visual cortex,
الوجوه الجذابة قادت النشاط العصبي بقوة في القشرة البصرية،
despite the fact that they were thinking about a person's identity
على الرغم من أنهم كانوا يفكرون حول هوية الشخص
and not their beauty.
وليس جمالهم.
Another group similarly found automatic responses to beauty
وبالمثل وجدت مجموعة أخرى الردود التلقائية على الجمال
within our pleasure centers.
ضمن مراكز المتعة لدينا.
Taken together, these studies suggest
تقترح هذه الدراسات معا
that our brain automatically responds to beauty
أن دماغنا تلقائيا يستجيب للجمال
by linking vision and pleasure.
من خلال ربط الرؤية والمتعة.
These beauty detectors, it seems,
كاشفات الجمال هذه على ما يبدو،
ping every time we see beauty,
تعمل في كل مرة نرى الجمال،
regardless of whatever else we might be thinking.
بغض النظرعن أي شيء قد يكون في تفكيرنا.
We also have a "beauty is good" stereotype embedded in the brain.
لدينا أيضا "الجمال هو أمر جيد" فالصورة النمطية جزء لا يتجزأ من الدماغ.
Within the orbitofrontal cortex,
داخل القشرة المخية الجبهية.
there's overlapping neural activity
هناك تداخل النشاط العصبي.
in response to beauty and to goodness,
استجابة على الجمال والخير،
and this happens even when people aren't explicitly thinking
وهذا يحدث حتى عندما الناس لا تفكر صراحةً
about beauty or goodness.
عن الجمال أو الخير.
Our brains seem to reflexively associate beauty and good.
أدمغتنا يبدو أنها غرائزيا تربط الجمال بالجيد.
And this reflexive association may be the biologic trigger
وهذه الاتحاد الغرائزي قد يكون الزناد البيولوجي
for the many social effects of beauty.
لكثير من الآثار الاجتماعية للجمال.
Attractive people receive all kinds of advantages in life.
يتلقى الناس الجذابين جميع أنواع المزايا في الحياة.
They're regarded as more intelligent,
إنهم يُعتبرون أكثر ذكاءً،
more trustworthy,
وجديرون أكثر بالثقة،
they're given higher pay and lesser punishments,
يتم منحهم رواتب أعلى وعقوبات أقل،
even when such judgments are not warranted.
حتى عندما تكون هذه الأحكام ليس لها ما يبررها.
These kinds of observations reveal beauty's ugly side.
هذه الأنواع من الملاحظات تكشف عن الجانب القبيح للجمال.
In my lab, we recently found
في مختبري، وجدنا مؤخراً
that people with minor facial anomalies and disfigurements
الأشخاص الذين لديهم شذوذ وتشوه طفيف في الوجه
are regarded as less good, less kind,
يعتبرون أقل جودة، أقل طيبة،
less intelligent, less competent and less hardworking.
أقل ذكاءً، وأقل كفاءة وأقل اجتهاداً.
Unfortunately, we also have a "disfigured is bad" stereotype.
للأسف، لدينا أيضا "المشوه السيئ "كصورة نمطية.
This stereotype is probably exploited and magnified
ربما تكون هذه الصورة النمطية واستغلالها وتضخيمها
by images in popular media,
من خلال الصور في وسائل الإعلام الشائعة،
in which facial disfigurement is often used as a shorthand
التي تشوه الوجه وغالبا ما تستخدمه باعتباره اختزال
to depict someone of villainous character.
لإعطاء الإنطباع أن الشخص شرير.
We need to understand these kinds of implicit biases
نحن بحاجة إلى فهم هذه الأنواع من التحيز الضمني
if we are to overcome them
إذا أردنا التغلب عليها
and aim for a society in which we treat people fairly,
ونهدف إلى مجتمع حيث نتعامل مع الناس بشكل عادل،
based on their behavior and not on the happenstance of their looks.
استنادا إلى سلوكهم وليس على المصادفة التي تخص أشكالهم.
Let me leave you with one final thought.
اسمحوا لي أن أترك لكم فكرة نهائية واحدة.
Beauty is a work in progress.
الجمال هوعمل في تقدم.
The so-called universal attributes of beauty
ما يسمى عالمياً بسمات الجمال
were selected for during the almost two million years of the Pleistocene.
تم اختيارهم خلال تقريباً مليوني سنة من العصر الحديث.
Life was nasty, brutish and a very long time ago.
كانت الحياة سيئة، وحشية ومنذ وقت طويل جدا.
The selection criteria for reproductive success from that time
معايير اختيار النجاح للإنجاب في ذلك الوقت
doesn't really apply today.
لا تنطبق إطلاقاً اليوم.
For example,
مثلاًً،
death by parasite is not one of the top ways that people die,
الموت بسبب الطفيليات ليس أحد أهم أسباب الوفاة اليوم،
at least not in the technologically developed world.
على الأقل ليس في تكنولوجيا العالم المتقدم.
From antibiotics to surgery,
من المضادات الحيوية إلى الجراحة،
birth control to in vitro fertilization,
تحديد النسل إلى الإخصاب في المختبر،
the filters for reproductive success are being relaxed.
مرشحات للنجاح الإنجابي يتم تخفيفها.
And under these relaxed conditions,
وفي ظل هذه الظروف المريحة،
preference and trait combinations are free to drift
التفضيل والسمات الموروثة تُصبح حرة في الإنجراف
and become more variable.
وتُصبح متعددة أكثر.
Even as we are profoundly affecting our environment,
حتى ونحن نُؤثر في بيئتنا بعمق،
modern medicine and technological innovation
الطب الحديث والابتكار التكنولوجي
is profoundly affecting
يؤثر تأثيرا عميقا
the very essence of what it means to look beautiful.
على جوهر ما يعنيه أن تبدو جميلاً.
The universal nature of beauty is changing
الطبيعة العالمية للجمال تتغير
even as we're changing the universe.
بينما نقوم بتغيير الكون.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)